90% of the battle in research is
actually finding the right problems.
This is Nimit Sohoni, Stanford PhD, AI
researcher, and previously a quant at
Citadel. And I asked him about both AI
research and quant careers. Do you have
any advice for someone who wants to move
into AI research? If you want to sort of
switch from a swee track to AI track,
there's got to be something behind it,
right? We compared and contrasted these
roles, which had some surprising
insights.
Yeah, I think you know, quant actually
probably has a better work-life balance
than AI. Unlike in tech, you know, one
thing I was surprised by, you know,
culturally is how tight-lipped people
are in finance, even within a firm. We
also went deep into what he's actually
working on now. The main challenge of
transformers is that Here's the full
episode.
[Music]
When you think about the opportunities
that are not available to you without a
PhD, what comes to mind?
Yeah, so I think
you know, there's not really too many
opportunities that are, you know,
actually unavailable to to people
without a PhD, but some of them just get
a lot easier with PhDs.
I mean, so academia is an obvious one
that does require a PhD.
That was never something I was super
interested in for a lot of reasons, but
I think some
some roles that are
definitely a PhD opens a lot of doors to
are
kind of the two that
two that I've had experience with. One
is like, you know, sort of doing
industry research in
AI like I'm doing now or, you know,
you know, back in the day there were,
you know, a few different like industry
research in computer science or
mathematics was a little bit more
diverse, but more and more people are
converging towards AI. So, I'll just say
like AI research is is one of them where
having a PhD helps or
not that you you know, a lot of people
do AI research without a PhD, but you
know, the type and shape of the role can
look different. And another one is
quantitative finance. So again, a lot of
people go into quant you know, out of
undergrad, but certainly having a PhD
like uh
opens you up to, you know, some some
sort of different opportunities and it
can be a lot easier to get your foot in
the door there.
So, if if we think concretely, let's say
I was going for an AI researcher role or
something like that. Are you saying the
PhD helps you in that first step of
filtering or does it help somewhere else
in the process in getting one of those
roles? Yeah, so I think it's it's both.
So, certainly it's a lot easier to get
an interview if you've differentiated
yourself from the pack in some way.
Um
you know, just
applying for AI research role at a, you
know, top firm
can be can be difficult, you know, if
you don't have, you know, whatever the,
you know, right schools quote unquote on
your resume, the right internships, the
right connections, whatever.
But it's certainly doable. And then I
guess like I I I think like more less
transactionally, having a or like doing
the PhD can
like develop like a key critical skill
set that can help you
as
along your path towards becoming a great
AI researcher.
But of course, you know, there is an
argument for being thrown into the fire
as well and just like kind of learning
on the job.
And that's certainly an option that
works for for many people.
I think have you know,
there's some things that are harder to
do in industry than in academia. Like
kind of the more exploratory first
principles like fundamental research
without necessarily like a direct
application. You know, in industry
definitely skews a lot heavier towards
the applied side of things.
But I think like having that fundamental
background can be very valuable
depending on what kind of research
you're targeting. You mentioned the the
type and the shape of the role could be
different if you had a PhD versus not.
Could you give a example what you mean?
If you're if you're working on more like
engineering heavy stuff in AI, so you
know, building, you know, training or
evaluation infrastructure,
you know, working on like, you know,
data processing, things like that. Those
are not things like a PhD is really
necessary for at all. I'd say if you
want to do more like sort of pie in the
sky type stuff like, you know,
architecture design, things like that,
a PhD can be you know, can be helpful
there because you know, you have more
time to kind of explore directions that
may not pay off in the short term. Um
but you know, again, there there
examples of people being successful in
you know, without a PhD with or without
a PhD in both both domains.
So, I think like if your only goal is to
be an AI researcher and you're not
super, you know, tied to the, you know,
the particular type of work you do, you
just really want to get into the field,
a PhD is definitely not necessary. But I
think like if you're um if you're still
in like the sort of exploration phase of
your career and you
want to um find like a, you know,
problem that really, you know, draws
your interest,
then a PhD can can be a good way to do
that.
You mentioned the PhD skill set or
something that you you kind of develop
when you get a PhD. What what is that
skill set? I I would say like 90% of the
battle in in research is actually
finding the right problems. Um so, you
know, you you have to find a problem
that is, you know, interesting, it's
meaningful that, you know, people are
actually going to care if you solve it.
You have to, you know, sometimes
convince people it's interesting because
they might not have thought about it the
same way.
And then then you have to execute.
And you need to make sure it's a problem
that's appropriately scoped that is
actually tractable for you to make
progress on. So, you know, I think like
all of those things were were not skills
that I had had developed. You know, it
was more, you know, just just like
execution was was my strength. And so,
definitely that was a, you know, big
learning process for me during the PhD
is like that sort of like research taste
and problem selection. And this is
something that, you know,
just like being immersed in the field,
you know, really helps with. You know,
once you've read enough papers, you
know, talked to enough people, you kind
of get a sense of the patterns and and
trends that are going on in the in the
field.
You mentioned the research taste and
finding the right problems. If you could
kind of condense what you learned in
your PhD, is there is there maybe some
top tips that kind of lead to you
finding the right problems? I would say
the the main things that
um
I find useful are just, you know,
keeping abreast of the current current
literature. Just reading, you know, as
many as many papers as you can. It
doesn't have to be reading them like end
to end, just like skimming abstracts,
you know, seeing what's going on, what
are people thinking about. Um
and yeah, I think the other thing is
just working your way up. So, you know,
initially earlier in your career, you
want to attack like, you know, very
small sub problems that are
you know, you're reasonably likely to
make progress on, right? So,
one example you know, example of this
can be like you take a, you know, method
and you try to extend it to some like,
you know, special case or some something
like slightly different from the
original application. And then as you as
you go on
and as you mature as a researcher, you
can start tackling like bigger and
bigger problems. So,
you know, not just like kind of
extending previous work, but maybe
coming up with like totally new ideas,
things like that. So, I think there is,
you know, a gradual stage of maturation
as a researcher and I think you know,
some people do try to skip those steps
and I think that's generally, you know,
it inadvisable, I think. You mentioned
keeping abreast of the the literature.
What's the go-to spot for you to kind of
get your feed of the hot research paper
to read? Honestly, Twitter is one of the
probably the the main way that I keep up
with papers. I think if you
follow
enough to that, so that's usually the
first way I find out about stuff.
Obviously, you know, just like talking
to people, you know, co-workers and so
on. But yeah, I think X is my go-to. So,
I try to I try to curate my feed in in
such a way that it's uh mostly
yeah, machine learning papers and
pictures of cute animals. Do you have
like a good starting point for someone
who's like just wants to plug in? I
pretty much like, you know, started with
following people I knew from Stanford
and you know, elsewhere, you know,
professors whose papers I'd read like,
you know, prominent people at big labs
and so on. And then like anytime, you
know, they tweet a paper, they like a
paper or something like that,
if it's if it's interesting to me, I
just click on that and I, you know,
follow all the people, you know, tagged
in or associated with that work.
And that's, yeah, so I sort of sort of
grew my follow list organically via
that.
I understand after your PhD, you became
a quantitative researcher at Citadel.
Where were you in your career and why'd
you decide to become a quant?
>> Yeah, I joined Citadel Securities after
graduation for my PhD.
And so, there yeah, so basically I I
actually interned there right before the
summer right before graduating.
And I liked it a lot. Reason I decided
to intern,
just kind of I wanted to see what else
was out there. I had had a few friends
who had interned at Citadel
at Citadel Securities and you know,
enjoyed it or other quant firms. And I
was
just kind of curious, you know, by that
point I'd been working AI research for
like four to five years.
And
yeah, like I said, I I was generally,
you know, when I entered my PhD, I was
interested in careers in which I could
apply my interests in mathematics and
computation. And so, I think the three
major
careers of that form at the time were,
you know, machine learning research,
which I already had experience with. Uh
you know, quantitative finance. And then
the last one maybe quantum computing,
but um you know, it was a much smaller
uh sort of uh domain and one I had no
experience with, although that one's
also kind of blowing up these days. So,
yeah, quant finance um I was just just
kind of curious and you know, I'd heard
good things and so um I decided to
intern um and uh I ended up liking it a
lot. I think it was uh you know,
refreshing in some ways.
Um you know, like I said, the PhD is a
grind, you know, you can burn out at
various points and um it was kind of a
fresh uh fresh set of problems,
um totally different environment. Well,
it's funny that you say that the grind
of the PhD, you kind of took a break to
become a quant at Citadel because I've
heard that the the work culture is
pretty intense at these finance
companies. Is that the case?
Yeah, so that is the reputation, but uh
I think
that definitely varies a lot based on
the team you're on, the firm you're at.
Um yeah, I personally I had a pretty
great work-life balance as funny as that
might sound um as a quant. Um you know,
I think one reason is that um
you know, traders typically uh will work
you know, trading hours or whatever
calendar in. You know, of course there
are markets all over the world, you
know, APAC uh you know, um Europe and so
on, but uh you know, in the US, US
traders are typically working uh you
know, around US uh trading hours and you
know, of course a little bit before and
after just uh to prepare and and and
stuff. And so, I think that generally
has a sort of trickle-down effect on the
culture where you know, most people are
just kind of um you know, really uh
clustered working around trading hours
and then don't take their work home uh
all too much. So, you know, even though
the work can be done at any time, I
think it just that is sort of how how
the office culture operates. Yeah, when
it comes to quantitative finance or
quant work, how would you describe the
work? It really really depends a lot on
both um the you know, team you're on,
like the sector you focus on. Um you
know, whether you're at a hedge a hedge
fund or a market maker, whether you're
like front office or or back office
quant. Um and uh you know, that of
course the company. And so, you know,
some quants will spend all their time
just like on alpha generation. So, you
know, generating new uh you know,
trading strategies and uh you know,
backtesting them and and so on and then
putting them into practice and
monetizing them. Um you know, I mean, so
well, some people will focus just on the
alpha, some people will focus on the you
know, monetization. Or you can be, you
know, like a risk quant. So, you're
basically um not necessarily generating
strategies at all, but just like um you
know, trying to uh come up with metrics
to capture uh risk and you know, avoid
that or reduce risk without reducing you
know, cutting into profits. Um you might
be um
you you might be doing like data
analysis. So, uh you might have like a
ton of like historical like trade data
and stuff and analyzing them in various
ways and and so on. So, um yeah, I think
uh
yeah, um yeah, like I said, like you
know, hedge fund versus market making or
they're they're actually very different
problems. So, I think uh the thing that
unifies all of them is really um you
know, having a strong math background.
Like in the day-to-day, let's say
you know, your
your project that you're currently
working on, like what would that look
like? What would the shape of that
problem look like and how does math
concretely play a role? You know,
depending on what sector you're in, you
know, there's a lot of different uh math
that will come into play. I mean, you
know, the sort of the backbone of
finance is stochastic calculus. So, I
think that comes up almost everywhere.
Um but then there are other things like,
you know, uh numerics, numerical
optimization, um
numerical interpolation, things like
that. Um you know, machine learning of
course is, you know, now more and more
firms are um like getting into getting
really deep into the you know, deep
learning space even like establishing
their own uh research um
research arms that do like LLM type
research and and stuff like that. Um
yeah, numerical linear algebra, um
yeah, so so there there's a lot of
different math and it's actually very uh
like it's actually very diverse in terms
of what uh
you know, people are always trying to um
come up with ways to
apply like different uh different fields
of math to quant. I think some of it is
just for for fun kind of, you know, um
because uh you know, quants are such a
mathy intellectual bunch, but there
there is actually a lot that uh you
know,
underpins the entire field. So, yeah, I
mean, I think yeah, stochastic
stochastic calculus is is probably the
most unifying part. Like that's kind of
the um you know, finance 101 type math.
So, uh you mentioned coding a lot as a
quant and I have had some friends who
were SWEs at Citadel and these various
companies. I understand the roles are
quite different. How do quants and SWEs
typically collaborate at these
companies?
Really depends a lot on the company. You
know, some some companies like, you
know, Jane Street for instance, like the
number of people who are called quants
is actually very small. And you know,
traders themselves are quite technical
and like implement a lot of stuff. Um
and then of course they have like
software engineers as well. Um whereas
Citadel I think is a more quant forward
firm. So, I think you know,
you know, a quants might be
uh if not the largest like percentage of
employees, like it might be a like about
equal in terms of the technical staff.
Um and so
yeah, I think um you know, there can be
a lot of overlap in what a quant uh
quantitative researcher and what a you
know, software engineer does. And also,
you know, between a quant and a trader.
Um so, um
yeah, it it it kind of just depends.
Like at some firms I think it's more
divorced where quants are really doing
you know, the the strategy work and then
it's like kind of handed off to software
engineers to implement. Um but at other
firms I think uh you you might do a bit
of both because uh you know, of course
like the the person like
if if they have the implementational
skills, the person best posed to like
actually implement something is the
person who like understands all the you
know, reasons and you know, uh edge
cases and things like that. Um and so um
yeah, like I said, I you know, I did a
ton of coding um mostly in C++ also some
Python. You know, if you were to compare
and contrast finance and tech generally
uh across these roles, uh what what
comes to mind?
So, I think a lot of the skill set first
of all is actually quite similar. Um
yeah, like I said, um you know, math and
math and computer science were my main
interests and I wanted a job that would
leverage both of them. And I think
that's been the case in quant and that's
also been the case um in um you know, in
AI research that I've done. Um and so
you know, I I knew nothing about finance
when I before I joined Citadel
Securities, but um you know, I read a
few textbooks recommended that were
recommended by people and um you know,
that was really all all I needed um
and um yeah, from there I just you know,
drew upon my sort of technical skills. I
think like AI research is is a lot of
the same way. I think if you have really
strong fundamentals, you can pick up uh
you know, pick up the rest. Uh
So, um yeah, in terms of technical
skills, I don't think it was you know,
really a rough transition um either
going you know, going either way. Um I
think uh you know, obviously the you
know, culture is different. Uh you know,
SF versus New York, uh those kind of
things. Um yeah, work work hours I would
say
yeah, I think you know, quant actually
probably has a better work-life balance
than AI. Um you know, it's particularly
the um level of competition in AI right
now. Um like uh you know, it's it's just
a very competitive space and so one of
the ways you can gain a competitive
advantage is just like by outworking
your competition and that kind of is you
know, what happens uh in in practice a
lot lot of places. I know a lot of
people
who are just like working around the
clock. I've heard insane stories about
the comp structures at quantitative
finance firms. Is that all true? Like is
it
heavily bonus weighted and
uh I've also heard stuff about garden
leave. So, yeah, in terms of comp yeah,
I think one thing is like, you know,
there's not really standardized levels
like there are in tech. You know, you
you can't just say, you know, it's not
like someone is just like IC5 and you
kind of know like what you know, kind of
pay bands there they they um what what
they're making. Uh it's it's uh yeah, I
think comp is really driven by
a few things. Um you know, how the
company does that year, how your team
does that year. Um
if you are really on like the alpha side
of things, like you know, how you how
your particular strategies did that
year. Um and then um of course there's
like uh other things that play into it
like seniority both in terms of, you
know, hierarchy if you're at one of the
firms that you know, does have a kind of
explicit hierarchy or in terms of like
uh you know, just like tenure at the
firm or years of experience, things like
that. And so, um
yeah, I think you know,
quant firms I I think are more secretive
and you know, partly because of the you
know, relative lack of standardization.
So, um it is kind of opaque uh in terms
of like how those factors actually
combine uh for your final comp. But um
yeah, I think it you know, it can be
very bonus driven if you're really on
the alpha side of things and that
attracts some people to that kind of
thing where they really would just want
like as they would want to be as exposed
as possible to I guess like the fruits
of their labor. But it is uh you know,
the downside is it can be much riskier
business as well. Um so, yeah, it's just
more variable. But like if you're, you
know, more back office type thing, I
think the comp is, you know, probably a
little bit more deterministic if you're
not, you know, directly as high to alpha
generation. Yeah, it's interesting. I
mean, cuz we were talking about AI
research versus quants. And obviously,
being a quant is
uh famous for earning a lot if you have
generated a lot of alpha. I hear
compensation like easily in the millions
for for a lot of these people.
Um
but at the same time, AI research also
popped off, too. You know, if you're in
the top 1% of either of these firms,
you're going to do very well. Yeah, I
mean, yeah, they're kind of crazy.
Um yeah, I mean, these these things
really do exist where people are making
like NBA player salaries and stuff. I
think, you know, for the for the median
case, uh
yeah, it's still it's still very good,
but I think uh yeah, it's it's uh not
not exactly that outlandish. Um yeah,
sorry. You you also mentioned stuff
about NDAs and stuff and and garden
leave.
Uh so, or sorry, non-competes, I guess.
So, yeah, I think um you know, so
finance firms are are very
you know, they're very serious about
this sort of thing. You know, unlike in
tech, uh you know, one thing I was
surprised by, you know, culturally is
how tight-lipped people are in finance,
even within a firm. Uh you know, there
is um things that you can and cannot
share across teams. And or people might
just want to be more secretive because,
uh you know, they're protective of their
alphas. And so, if you like know kind of
what they're doing, you can sort of
re-implement a similar thing and like
capture take over some of their alpha,
right? Because
uh it what what makes an alpha is that
it's, you know, secret. If if more the
more people know who know about it, like
the less profitable it's going to be for
any individual. And so, um yeah, I I
think it's, you know, quite secretive.
Uh you know, even even the firms that
are, you know, have a reputation for
being more open are are actually quite
secretive. Whereas in tech, you know,
people talk about things all the time.
And so, it was a bit jarring for me
returning to tech and like hearing like
people you know, talk about what they're
doing in like a, you know, very open way
is like, "Wow, like
you're just going to tell me that for
free?"
So, yeah, a non-compete is like, yeah,
probably the, you know, most notorious
part of this is, yes, a lot of firms
will
um have a clause in your, you know, in
in the contract you sign at the
beginning stating that you cannot work
for a competitor for a period of time
after you um after you leave the firm.
Uh and this period of time is typically
decided by the company when you when you
leave, but it can be um anywhere from
Well, it can be zero uh up to like 2
years. Uh I think I've heard like even
up to 3 years for for some places, but I
think that's rare. I think the norm is I
I would say the norm is like, you know,
6 months to 2 years.
Um and so, yeah, during this period,
you're
basically just paid to not work. Um
yeah, it's called garden leave because,
I guess, you know, you you sit at home
and garden or whatever.
Um and it's actually like
I mean, it's actually quite interesting
thing, you know, creates interesting
incentives for some people cuz you are
typically compensated quite well during
this garden leave period. So, um it's
not necessarily a you know, it's not
necessarily a downside for some people.
Um and yeah, basically the idea is like,
you know,
um
you won't, you know, leak ideas to your
competitors. And, you know, by the time
your garden is leave is over, you know,
if you have some special alphas or
trading strategies, um you know, 2 years
down the line, they're probably not even
relevant anymore. So, it doesn't even
matter. You mentioned the secrecy within
uh in quantitative finance. And I see a
natural incentive here to kind of be
uh hostile or I guess
competing within the the firm because
Yeah. My alpha is my alpha. I'm not
going to help you.
Did you ever feel that or see stories of
that? Yeah, no, it's it's definitely a
thing. Um you know, people are um yeah,
I think a lot of people are, you know,
reluctant or or or even forbidden to
talk about um
any details basically of what they what
they do. Uh you know, some people
That's you know, some people, you know,
won't even don't even like say what
sector uh you know, they work on.
Uh you know, at least across companies
and stuff like that. So, um yeah, I
think uh that that's definitely a thing.
You know, some some firms are set up
where it's like basically pods. So, you
know, one pod is just
responsible for basically all all of
their P&L. And then the firm takes a
cut. And so, you know, different pods
might be working on, you know, very
similar things unknowingly, right? But
they're not sharing any of the
information. Um and there is some logic
behind this um because uh the idea is
you want to have uncorrelated, uh you
know, um
uncorrelated returns. So, if all the
pods are like, you know, talking to each
other sharing ideas, you know, chances
are they're going to start doing very
similar things. And then, you know, that
exposes you to risk where, you know,
what if the thing you're doing is
actually wrong? And uh you know, you can
wipe out not just one pod, but entire
team of them. Whereas if people are
working independently, um then, you
know, that's that's not that's less of a
risk.
Earlier, you mentioned a the top 1% of
AI researchers and quants are going to
do
extraordinarily well. I'm curious, what
sets the top 1% of AI researchers and
quants apart from the rest?
There are a lot of things. Uh I think
there are different ways to get to that
point as well. Can be raw technical
skill. Like some people are just really
really good at what they do, able to,
you know, the prototypical like 10 10x
engineer, that kind of thing. And they
just have you know, a
a better higher level of intuition and
or execution speed. Um
stuff like that. Um you know, of course,
there's politics involved. Like uh you
know, people who are better at playing
the
uh political game can, um you know, rise
up in the ranks. I think in quant, you
know, one thing is that it is a bit, you
know, it's harder to game the system
because there are kind of hard metrics
that it it's easier to evaluate how
someone does. Especially, you know, if
you're an alpha quant, you know, it's
quite clear, right? Like if you
implement a strategy, um and you make
the firm a ton of money, like that's
obviously going to be recognized. Um I
think, you know, in in AI, you know, it
can be a little bit harder. But if of
course, the I mean, the analog might be
like you publish like a seminal paper,
like you make a true breakthrough in the
field. Um you know, you you make, you
know, the models much better than um
yeah, that that sort of thing. So, um
yeah, I think it's Yeah, I guess it's
probably similar to, you know, other
domains. It's just a combination of
skill and like um you know, playing
playing the game.
I think being in the right place at the
right time has a lot to do with it. You
know, both in quant in terms of uh
seeing something before other people do
and then like making taking advantage
capitalizing on market trends and and
and turning that into a profit. Um or in
AI, you know, like having the right idea
at the right time.
When it comes to quant firms, I'm kind
of curious, there's all these tier lists
out there. What are the top firms and
why?
RenTech, uh like we talked about, is one
of the sort of mythical firms in the
space. Uh you know, you can't really
argue with their returns. Uh the
historical returns over like a, you
know, 20-year 30-year period, it's uh
pretty insane. Uh so, you know, RenTech
is maybe
you know, the gold standard, uh you
know, depending on who you ask. Um then
there are other firms like, uh you know,
the some of the slightly big bigger ones
like, you know, Jane Street, Citadel, uh
Jump Trading, Hudson River. Think those
are generally very well-regarded firms.
Um and, you know, having that kind of
thing on your resume can definitely be,
you know, an asset to to future quant
roles and things like that. So, um yeah,
very good firms. I think, you know,
great technical talent, uh great
returns, obviously. Um and then there
there are some like elite smaller ones.
Uh you know, similar to RenTech, like,
you know, smaller, more secretive, uh
less well-known, but still very very uh
excellent returns. Uh so, um yeah, TGS
uh is one. It's in Southern California.
Um yeah, XT X is another one. Uh newer
one of the newer firms. I think Radix is
another newer firm that's uh yeah, in in
that in that boat. So, yeah.
Are there any stories that you working
in the space that you think might be
interesting?
You know, finance firms do not mess
around. So, you hear stories about like,
you know,
people just doing, you know, dumb things
like, you know, traders uh or quants
having like an internal WhatsApp group
uh where they, you know, talk about
strategies. And they're like like, uh
so, as a quant, you have like trading
restrictions. You have to get all trades
pre-approved. And so, of course, if
you're you know, someone who works in
equities or something, you know, you
probably are not going to be able to
trade those tickers at all. Uh but, you
know, people try to get around it with
with their little WhatsApp groups or
whatever like telling their friends to,
you know, buy these buy these stocks or
something, split the profits or
whatever.
Um if that happens and and you get found
out, you know, um they're going to go
after you. You'll you'll get fired,
obviously. There'll be lawsuits. You can
you can even go to jail. Uh yeah,
there's like a um
few stories about this uh because it is
it is against the law. And so, um yeah,
I've heard heard horror stories about
this. They they That's one of the things
they tell you about in training,
actually. It's like uh yeah, do not do
this. Um similar with like non-competes,
you know, people going to competitors or
starting their own thing or something
and like
uh
getting accused of taking strategies and
stuff like that. Um yeah, they all these
firms have like elite legal teams. And
yeah, just not something you want to
mess with.
I've heard that in quantitative finance
that it's kind of intense sometimes. Or
rather, people may get fired uh very
often.
Did you ever have like you just were
working with someone that kind of just
disappeared?
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, yes, that that does
happen. Um
yeah, I think it's interesting in quant
because um
Well, as I said, yeah, your comp comp is
a function of many things, among uh
among which is seniority. And so, I
think your job security can actually be
kind of U-shaped because senior quants,
like, you know, even if they're very
good, they just get very expensive after
a while because that's sort of what the,
you know, market rate is for for senior
quants. And so, you know, even a even a
good quant, you know, can stop being
worth it after a while. Where where
where as like earlier career quants, you
know, um
you can uh you know, they might be very
good and also not command, uh you know,
as high of a uh salary. So, yeah, the
job shape security not not U-shaped like
kind of like an inverse parabola almost.
Um and yeah, I mean, people certainly
get fired. It's a
quant in general, I think, has a culture
of um you know, um
well, one is like up or out and two is
like, you know, just trimming the low
performers. Um
and again, I think this can become, you
know, especially easy if you're like
more like on the on the alpha side.
Like, if you're just not making money,
like it can be pretty clear. But uh in
in general, like even for like, you
know, engineers, um yeah, I think there
is this kind of culture. Um yeah,
traders, of course, it's yeah, since
they're, you know, making trades and
stuff again, it's like very easy to
monitor. So, I think that can be even
more more brutal.
Why did you leave
um Citadel to join Cartesia?
When I joined Citadel, it was partly cuz
I was just interested in learning about
a new problem domain and like um you
know, learning some learning some new
stuff. Uh you know, learning about
finance in general, I think, was also
like kind of interesting to me. Um and
uh yeah, I think, you know, I became
more financially literate as a result of
things and and and stuff like that.
Like, it was it was a it was a great
learning experience for me and I was
kind of optimizing for like growth
potential partially as well.
Um but yeah, I mean, by that point, you
know, I'd been at Citadel for, you know,
a couple years and was um yeah, I think
um
you know, like it's it's sort of like
you you you growth, uh you know, at most
places will kind of like accelerate for
a while and then like so sort of taper
off. But I think there was still a lot
more to to be learned had I decided to
continue on that path. But I um you
know, I saw what was going on in the
field of AI. Uh you know, when I
graduated actually was right before um
ChatGPT came out. And so, I think a lot
had changed even since I joined Citadel.
Um and I heard that um you know, the
founders of Cartesia were starting this
company. Uh and for context, I knew all
of them from my PhD at Stanford. They
were actually all in Chris Ray's lab
with me.
Um I knew Albert pretty well. Um and so,
um yeah, I had, you know, tons of
respect for them. They're, you know,
great researchers. I worked uh you know,
pretty closely with some of them. Um you
know, Albert was a good friend of mine.
Knew the
uh knew the other guys. And so, it just
seemed like a great opportunity uh and a
great time to get into get back into the
field of AI when things were sort of
taking off. And I thought it would be
great um in terms of you know, personal
and technical growth. Also, the
opportunity to join a small startup um
was definitely uh something that was
interesting to me.
And uh kind of like shape the company
and the culture uh you know, as one of
the earlier employees. And so, um
yeah, it was really um yeah, I think uh
yeah, it was all about all about growth,
getting back into AI. And um and I think
like, you know, um
there's like a definitely a different
risk profile, I think. When I
uh graduated my PhD, I was kind of more
like risk-averse. Uh you know, quant was
like a you know, stable, you know,
lucrative opportunity that um you know,
was the right choice for me at that
time. Um now that I had sort of
established myself a little bit, gotten
some of that stability, I thought it
was, you know, opportune time to take a
risk.
Cartesia, I guess it If you could give
us some context on kind of the primary
problem the company's solving and just
like what the company's about. Uh yeah,
we are a voice AI company. You know, our
current mission is to build sort of the
next generation of voice voice AI voice
AI and a platform for that. So, what
that means is we do um you know, our
flagship product is text to speech. Um
we um you know, we also have products
around speech to text, uh you know,
voice agents,
um and um yeah, stuff like that. And um
yeah, I think, you know, we believe
voice AI is the future. Um you know,
it's already
it's a it's actually one of the fastest
growing areas of AI. Um you know, people
are using voice AI um in you know, many
applications, you know, call center is
being one of the predominant ones, but
also a bunch of bunch of applications in
entertainment, you know, a bunch of like
um you know, companions, like a bunch of
a bunch of different things. And uh so,
that's uh that's kind of the the product
uh set we're building.
Um and um
yeah, in terms of um you know, why why
do we choose voice? I so, I think, you
know, voice is actually um
a very interesting test bed for a lot of
uh research ideas that are um
um that we're exploring.
Uh so, we're um you know, we also have
like a sort of research arm of the
company that focused on kind of
longer-term research around uh you know,
around long context, around
multimodality,
um things like continual learning and
and memory, uh you know, test time
compute and in general, like, you know,
our our our our, you know, sort of
overall like even higher higher level
goal is to build real-time um you know,
systems that are truly intelligent and
that you can like interact with and that
can learn from experience. And so, I
think you know, building these, you
know, voice agents, you know, speech to
speech models and so on is um you know,
it uh requires you to kind of um you
know, solve some of these problems for
the, you know, sort of eventual eventual
idea of like a kind of like always-on
assistant, personal assistant. When it
comes to this voice AI space, who are
the top competitors? So, um our main
competitor is a company called Eleven
Labs. Um
they're, you know, another voice AI
company basically. Um
and uh yeah, so they I think had about a
18-month head start on us. Uh yeah, I
actually used to play with Eleven Labs,
you know, long before Cartesia was ever
a thing just like kind of make like, you
know, fun videos and and and whatnot.
And so, um yeah, it's you know, a very
very similar um
company, I think. Uh you know, where
Cartesia stands out, I think, is um you
know, we have um
sort of a focus on
um you know, things like latency. So, um
you know, low latency is really
important for a lot of voice AI
applications. You know, for naturalness,
you know, like the conversation we're
having now, you know, you can't afford
to have, you know, you know, second
pause in between like each uh each uh
um you know, each turn of the
conversation. You know, that just really
breaks the sort of illusion and uh and
um immersion. And so, you know, latency
is really important for uh you know, a
lot of our customers. Um
yeah, you know, we're continuing to try
to push the boundary of sequence
modeling and stuff to get, you know,
better and better quality um without
compromising on latency.
Um and then um you know, going into like
more end-to-end systems as well. So,
right now the way voice agents are um
typically implemented is uh you have a
speech to text system that transcribes
some text. Uh then you feed this into a
language modeling backbone. And then you
have a text to speech system that will
take the text that is output by the
language model and you know, speak the
result. Um but this has a lot of
problems uh in terms of uh latency
again, in terms of naturalness because
it's kind of non end-to-end system. Uh
so, there's a lot of, you know, loss in
between each of these components and so
on.
Um and so, yeah, that's uh you know, one
thing that we're trying to build
towards. Um but even right now, I would
say, you know, even if you just look at
our text to speech products, I think,
you know, we're definitely um right up
there as, you know, one of the leaders
in the space. Um I think um yeah, you
know, Eleven wins on some languages, we
win on some. Um you know, I would say we
have like better voice cloning, things
like that. So, um yeah, we're trying to
be become number one in everything. Uh
uh
But yeah, I think, you know, like I
said, voice AI is a very fast-growing
space. And so, a lot of people are
jumping into the space, but I think the
the pie is very large.
What does it look like if Cartesia
completely destroys Eleven Labs?
I think we already win in terms of
things like latency, in terms of cost.
Um I think if we can conclusively win in
terms of quality not just for, you know,
subset of tasks, uh you know, and not
just for a subset of things like uh but
um you know, there are many things that
people care about for text to speech
quality. There's um you know, just
adhering to the transcript. So, actually
reading what is put, you know, in front
of the model, which is, you know, can be
surprisingly hard, especially if you
have different languages, especially if
you know, special characters, you know,
repetitions, whatever. Uh you know, all
models struggle with this. Uh but there
is also naturalness. Like, does it
really sound like a person saying this
or does it sound robotic? You know, of
course, like people a lot of a lot of
applications actually care about
naturalness even more than just
transcript fidelity.
Um
and then, you know, of course, there are
all the, you know, speed and and and
things like that.
Um and then there are features like, you
know, voice cloning, accent
localization. So, you know, taking my
voice and making have a different
accent, uh things like that. Um you
know, controllability, you know, speed,
emotion, um
things like that. And so, um
yeah, like I said, I think you know, we
have better quality in in some areas,
maybe worse than in in some others. You
know, we'd like to get to number one in
um you know, in as many categories as
possible, right? And so, I think that's
that's sort of the thing, right? Like,
um you know, switching costs exist even
in AI. I think, you know, depending on
the size of the customer, like some
customers are reluctant to switch over
from, you know, one thing to the other.
Um you know, obviously startups can be
more nimble, but you know, uh when when
you're talking about enterprise scale,
um you know, this matters. And but like,
if you are, you know, conclusively show
that you're better in every way, then I
guess like at some point it becomes hard
to hard to argue for not switching.
I imagine you could have worked at a big
lab, Open AI, DeepMind, etc. What's the
main difference in working in an AI
startup versus one of these big AI labs?
Big labs have obviously amazing
resources, you know, they have all the
compute in the world. Um you know, tons
of researchers and and so on. I think
one thing is that like the the the flip
side of that is that um I think big labs
can sometimes be more averse to sort of
out of the box ideas and a little bit
more susceptible to group think or like
sort of overarching trends in the field
and like less willing to take a risk
on
something different.
And then you know that that makes sense
right because you know with sort of
these you know great resources you know
that's there's a lot of cost to
investigating new ideas that don't that
don't turn out well.
Whereas a startup I think you're a bit
more nimble you're able to you know
you're able to be a little little bit
more exploratory if you do it
strategically
and sort of challenge the orthodoxy
in in that in that way. And so that was
one of the things like I mentioned that
drew me to Cartesian you know Albert has
you know a lot of interesting ideas that
I think don't necessarily go go with the
like the accepted grain like you know in
you know around the time Mamba came out
you know people were kind of like of the
opinion a lot a lot of people were of
the opinion that like you know sequence
modeling was kind of a solved problem
and all you need is scale. Like you just
take the transformer recipe and you just
scale it further and further.
Yeah I mean Albert showed that you know
that's not necessarily the case right
with Mamba
that you can actually get real
advantages um
in terms of in terms of things like you
know efficiency computational efficiency
but also like even in terms of just like
raw quality.
You know state space models can be
advantageous for a lot of classes of
problems or like things like hybrid
models where you take some state space
model layers some transformer layers
things like that.
You know another more recent work that
we put out at Cartesian was this idea of
H nets where
so yeah for for context the way that
text modeling is usually done is you
take you know you take you know raw text
you know sequence of characters or you
know UTF 8 bytes or whatever and then
you compress it or you know you
represent it as these things called
tokens which are basically like little
pieces of words or sub words. And then
you run modeling over that. So it's like
a two-stage pipeline.
You know we showed that
if you actually just go from the raw you
know raw characters
and you kind of learn this tokenization
you learn how to like draw these
boundaries in between groups of letters
instead you can actually get better
performance.
And so yeah that's the kind of thing you
know I think challenging accepted ideas
like that's the kind of thing that
appealed to me. For context you
mentioned state space models versus
transformer could you just give a quick
primer I guess. Without going into too
much I guess technical detail
you know
basically
the main challenge of transformers is
that the
you know the memory that they use at
inference time grows linearly with the
sequence length because what they do is
like you know they will take each token
and store you know a representation of
it in what's called the KB cache.
You know the key value cache and so as
you as your sequence grows longer and
longer like you're still storing all of
this information in context in your
memory. And so for very long sequences
you know this can get prohibitive both
in terms of you know computational cost
and in terms of memory.
SSMs are different because instead of
storing everything into you know
everything like in this uncompressed way
they take that information and they
compress it so the size of the state is
is is fixed. And so as a result like
your
you know the cost of doing a certain
step doesn't change with the length of
the sequence and you know the amount of
information you have to keep in memory
does not grow with the sequence length.
And so kind of an intuition you know
co-founder Albert Gu has a great blog on
this
is that SSMs are kind of like a brain.
You know the human brain also does not
store an unbounded amount of context.
You know it takes in information and it
processes it and it like you know keeps
it in this fixed size state which is you
know which is our brain. Of course you
can seemingly having a you know
unbounded state but via use of external
tools like you know writing stuff down
and so on. But the core you know the
core primitive remains fixed. Whereas
transformers are more like a database
where you can kind of recall anything in
the context. And so I think both of
these approaches are complementary
right?
And
yeah so you know we're currently
exploring
kind of you know extensions of that
analogy. But yeah I would say that's
kind of the the you know high level
thing.
Is the sequence just the input? So the
longer the prompt the longer the
sequence and therefore more memory
consumption at inference. That's right.
So the sequence is the prompt plus the
response. So you know as as the model is
generating the response you know the
context you know the context includes
what has been generated so far right? So
you can refer back to what you yourself
have said and then you'll figure out
what is you know what is the next
appropriate token to say. And so this
can get obviously especially large for
multi-turn conversations where
now the context includes like everything
that has been said in the entire
conversation up to that point. And so
you know beyond a point as I'm sure
we've all had experience with you know
you're chatting with these language
models you know sort of ceases to be you
know that useful maybe after you know
you know tens or something of turns and
you know it can be best to start a new
conversation. But the challenge with
that and you know of course other
companies are doing things to try and
sort of address or band-aid this you
know for instance like chat GPT now like
saves some like global context in
between conversations and stuff like
that. But it doesn't really truly learn
from you know from your personal
proclivities and and and preferences and
like the things you've asked it in the
past. Like there there is some semblance
of this of course but I wouldn't say
that it's like you know truly personal
yet and
in terms of like an actual
agent that is like kind of learning and
growing every day. Yeah you know I've
been using Cloud code a bunch and I
noticed occasionally it does this thing
it says it's compacting or something
like that. I imagine it's taking the
multi-turn conversation.
I don't know what it's doing just maybe
summarizing it and restoring it. Yep.
Yeah there are all there are all sorts
of different ways to kind of compress
the KB cache either
sort of mechanistically or kind of doing
like a you know textual summaries or
things like that. There yeah this is a
pretty active area of research as well.
You mentioned that the state space
models they have a compressed
representation of the KB cache or
and so I'm curious does that have a
trade-off in terms of the quality of
inference is it lossy? Yeah so there are
there are certainly trade-offs you know
um
the
yeah I think
depending on the task like so for very
like recall heavy you know or fact-based
tasks you know SSM pure SSM models can
lag transformers because like the
the ability of transformers to do this
kind of exact in context recall turns
out to be very helpful for this kind of
task. Whereas for you know for other
tasks that don't require this type of
thing
you know SSMs can can scale just as well
or better as transformers even for like
a fixed parameter budget you know let
alone inference budget.
You can you can
kind of get the best of both worlds you
know a lot of people have shown this
by doing a hybrid model so you just
basically interleave state space model
and transformer layers with you know
with some ratios. And so yeah Nvidia's
put out stuff like this even the Quinn
you know their latest Quinn models
follow this strategy as well. So yeah I
think the you know the cutting edge I
would say for for text is is probably in
these hybrid models at least in terms of
like what's what's out there for open
source.
But the interesting thing is that
you know for for other modalities like
audio it actually makes a lot of sense
to to have this compression as like a as
a explicit inductive bias. So using you
know SSMs
for for audio has proven you know very
useful for us. You know we found that it
actually improves performance. It's kind
of almost a free lunch you know you get
improved performance
improved quality and improved
performance at inference time. And the
reason is that sort of like
if you think about what these models are
doing you know
audio is you know depending on how you
represent it is a very like you know um
there's
there's very little information
contained in any one like you know time
step or token if you will of audio. It's
you know like a
frame of you know depending on what
you're doing like you know 10
milliseconds to 100 milliseconds. And so
you know one frame to the next doesn't
really vary that much and so you know
compressing these into you know sort of
fixed size state can actually like makes
a lot of sense as opposed to text which
is a much like sort of
densely informational modality. You know
one word to the next there is actually a
ton of
information contained in each of those
tokens. And so you know compression is
less
you know it's kind of already like
pre-compressed if if you're if you're
using a token level representation.
But but yeah even so I think you know
hybrid models I would say hybrid models
I think are are the future in in in that
regard.
I see okay. So it's because the modality
itself has I guess redundancy in the
data that means that this lossiness is
actually an asset rather than
a problem. Exactly. Yeah. So yeah I
think you know there's a lot of
interplay between modality and
architecture. It's definitely not
something you cannot design your
architecture independently of your data.
And so yeah kind of this like you know
co-design and like thinking about
you know modality multi-modality from a
fundamental level you know this is one
of you know the research problems that I
mentioned that like kind of drives
drives a lot of the work we do here.
When you think about companies that
focus on product versus research, what
pattern do you think is
most effective? Um so, I think, you
know, personally and and this is one of
you know, also one of the reasons I
decided to join Cartesia. I think it is
very important to have have both.
I think like so there are you know,
several startups popping out recently
that are really
you know, focused on core research and
not don't even necessarily have like an
idea how to productionize it or or turn
that into
you know, a product product or revenue
stream. Um I think like you know, I
personally am am fairly skeptical of
this approach. I think
you know, for a few reasons. I think
first of all, you know, you know, big
labs you know, have tons of resources
and also have you know, large teams
focused on this sort of thing. I think
um
Yeah, I think like
you know, ultimately the goal of a
company is to is to make money, right?
And so I think you know, eventually you
know, if you are if you are a company of
this form like you need to eventually
deliver like you know, massively
outsized returns you know, at some
point.
So I think you're you're taking a big
risk where it can kind of be all or
nothing type thing. Um I think the flip
side of it like a sort of product only
company that's built on AI models that
are built by other people. Um I think
that is like risky in the sense that you
don't have as much of a moat.
So you know,
like we saw this with you know,
initial chat GPT or you know, going from
GPT3 or GPT4, right? A lot of these
wrapper companies kind of just got made
obsolete by the fact that the base
models improved so much that they could
often just do what the wrapper was
trying to do
by by by themselves with without very
much scaffolding and so it became kind
of thing you can
just build build in-house rather than
needing another company to
you know, post process the output of
these outputs of these models. I think
like being in the intersection is
actually quite valuable for
you know, for many reasons. I think
having a product a real product that
customers use is something that can
drive the research. So you see firsthand
the issues
and you can use that to drive you know,
your next iteration of modeling you
know, try and fix these issues not as a
band-aid but like you know, from the
ground up right? Like from
at the model level itself. And so I
think having control over the models is
like very important when you're when
you're building an AI product. Um which
is not to say that like you know,
there's no room for any non-research
company. I think it just like
it has to be in the you know, right
right kind of right kind of space. Um
and so yeah, I think um
Cartesia has a great blend of research
and product. You know, we're very
I would say we're first and foremost a
product company. Uh but you know, we
want to build the best products we can
and we believe that that requires us to
actually solve some of these fundamental
research problems in order to do that.
I think there's a lot of people who want
to get into AI research. I mean I was
just talking with a friend today who's a
SWE and he's saying
I don't think software engineering is
going to be around in
10 years or something like that. So he's
been investigating. And I'm curious, do
you have any advice for someone who is
technical and wants to move into AI
research?
My my philosophy has always been to try
and build up my technical skills as much
as possible. I think you're if you're if
your fundamentals are good enough like
you know, at some point
you know,
the opportunities will just come to you
rather than the other way around. And so
I would say just focus on getting as
good as you can at you know, at coding
at you know, AI read tons of papers.
Yeah, I think math skills and math
intuition are really important. And so
that's that's what I've kind of been
optimizing for um you know, ever since
undergrad when I realized what I wanted
to do was at least you know, some
combination of math and computer
science. And so I've always more focused
on like kind of building up those
fundamentals and I think that is the way
to get your foot in the door. I think
like bigger companies it can be a bit
harder to pivot you know, teams or what
you work on. And so
uh for for someone like that I think you
just switching like teams or companies
can can be like you know, sort of the
only path forward. I think you you can
kind of get siloed in a little bit if
you're at a bigger company sometimes. I
do think you know, some companies are
better about it and you know, I have
seen people transition from SWEs to
research and and and stuff like that.
Um so I think you know, this is one of
the areas where getting a sort of
qualification on your
resume can be useful like getting a you
know, a master's in AI at least or
something like that can help
when when you're looking to make a sort
of lateral career change like that.
You're you're saying there's kind of two
common paths. One would be get more
education and use that qualification to
kind of pivot directly into AI research
or go to a startup where you can kind of
like mold yourself into an AI research
role.
That's kind of right but I think even if
you want to go to a startup, right? And
you want to but you want to sort of
switch from a SWE track to AI track like
there's got to be some
there's got to be something behind it,
right? Like you have to have some
evidence of a skill set whether it's
like sort of
organically grown or from you know, from
from schooling.
But I think it can probably be a lot
easier to get your foot in the door if
you have some evidence of of it on your
resume. So like let's say you were
you hired at Cartesia and then that
person comes to you and he's like, hey,
I want to do more AI research. In that
case, is that something where it's like
just flip the switch and next project is
AI research project? This has actually
has actually happened you know, in
Cartesia itself. You know, we have had
people transition
roles like that. So I think it is
definitely easier at a startup which is
it can be a bit more flexible just cuz
you know, everyone kind of knows
everyone and so
you can get a sense of you know, whether
this might be an appropriate career
change just by like kind of knowing the
person for a while. And so yeah, I mean
we've actually done you know, people
have done this in in Cartesia with with
you know, a lot of success.
Do you have a biggest regret when you
look back on your whole career? I mean I
I think I often overthink things and I
think I have spent a lot of time
regretting you know, past decisions that
turned out not to matter in the end and
I kind of regret the amount of time I
spent regretting other things. So you
know, I try I try to learn from that
now. You know, I think like you know,
don't sweat the small stuff like you
know,
you know, minor setbacks happen and they
happen but I think uh you know,
there's a risk of
you know, putting too much stress on
yourself and you're like beating
yourself up and and stuff like that. And
those are just like not productive ways
to spend your time and they don't make
anyone feel good and so I think yeah, I
try and you know, I try not to regret
stuff because yeah, I think it's just
not not a super good use of time. If you
had to go back in time and you could
give yourself some advice when you're
just entering the industry, what would
you say? Focus on building the deep
technical skills.
Yeah, don't waste time with like sort of
trifling stuff or spreading your
yourself too thin. Um yeah, just like
focus on
what you want to focus on I guess like
basically like the the skills that you
want to leverage in your day job just
like do those and get good at those and
you know, that's that's that's where you
should spend all your time at work. Um
and
yeah.
You make it sound so simple.
Maybe it is.
>> it is it is a simple it's kind of a
simple recipe that's very hard to
follow, right? Like it's very hard to
maintain that discipline.
It's kind of like you know, um
you know, what's the secret to being
healthier? It's you know, exercising and
eating right and those are things that
are just very much easier said than
done.
But yeah, I think
it is it is that simple.
Awesome. Cool. Well, thanks so much for
your time, Amit. Thanks for listening to
the podcast. I don't sell anything or do
sponsorships but if you want to help out
with the podcast, you can support by
engaging with the content on YouTube or
on Spotify. If you want to drop a
review, that will be super helpful. And
if there's any guests that you want to
bring on to, please let me know. I feel
like sourcing very senior ICs, there's
no well-studied list out there on Google
that I can just search this up. So if
there's someone in your org or at your
company who you really look up to and
you want to hear their career story, let
me know and I'll reach out to them.